Elisabeth Tooker Papers 1945-1994 Mss.Ms.Coll.84
American Philosophical Society
- Series III. Works by Tooker, 1949-1993
  Mostly unpublished works, including many papers written for graduate courses at the University of Arizona and at Radcliffe College. Most of the works are on Iroquois topics, but there are also graduate papers about Southwestern Indians, including the Navaho, Yumans, and Papago Indians. There are a number of works about the nineteenth century anthropologist Lewis H. Morgan, and there is one work on the Handsome Lake religion ("History of the Handsome Lake Church"). There are two drafts of Tooker's published article, "The United States Constitution and the Iroquois League." The earliest item in this series is Tooker's undergraduate honors thesis, "An Interpretation of the Navaho Death Complex with Comparisons to the Apache and Pueblo," written in April 1949 at Radcliffe College. This series also contains Tooker's master's thesis, "Papagos in Tucson: An Introduction to Their History, Community Life, and Acculturation," written at the University of Arizona in 1952, and her doctoral thesis, "Ritual, Power and the Supernatural: A Comparative Study of Indian Religions in Southwestern United States," written for Radcliffe College in March 1958.
  - A - L (Box 10)
    - "Acculturation, Urbanization and thePapagos", 1953
    - "American Anthropology in the Formative Years: The Case of the New York State Museum", 1993 Apr. 16
    - "The Anthropologist and the Informant"-- Pa, 1954?
    - "Archaeological Evidence for Seventeenth Century Iroquoian Dream Fulfillment Rituals"--with Marian E. White, 1967
    - "Chapayeka Masks"--Paper forAnthropology 203, 1950 May 25
    - "Comment on Dena's Ethnicity Session", 1992 Apr. 11
    - "Critique on Underhill's `SocialOrganization"'--Paper for Anthr. 299b, 1950 Apr. 3
    - "The Demise of the Susquehannocks: AWhodunit for Ethnohistorians", 1981
    - "An Essay on the Methodology of Durkheim, Radcliffe-Brown and Evans-Pritchard"--Paper for Social Relations 292, 1954 Nov.
    - "Ethnology and the Iroquois", 195-
    - "An Example of Values", 1952?
    - "Form and Function in Iroquois Ritual", 1970 May
    - "Ghosts: A Sociological and Psychological Study"--Paper for Social Relations 216 & 217, 1954 May 3
    - "The Historic Place of the Four Sacred Rituals in the Iroquois Midwinter Ceremonial", 1966
    - "History of the Handsome Lake Church", 1986
    - "How to Construct an Iroquois BarkLonghouse of the 17th Century"
      -See Ser.II, Iroquoia, Folder #3
    - "Informant-Anthropologist Relations"-- Paper for Social Relations 225a, 1955 Jan.
    - "An Interpretation of the Navaho Death Complex with Comparisons to the Apache and Pueblo"--Honors thesis at Radcliffe College, 1949 Apr.
    - "Introduction: A Sociological Critique of the Folk-Urban Concept", 1953 Jun. 3
    - "The Iroquois Diaspora", 1984 Oct.
      -See also Ser.II, Fort Stanwix National Monument
    - "Iroquois Religious Change", n.d.
    - "Iroquois Since 1820", 1978
    - "The Iroquois Village"
    - "Iroquois Worlds of the Nineteenth andTwentieth Centuries"
      -See Ser.III, "Iroquois Since 1820"
    - "Lewis H. Morgan and HisContemporaries", 1990
    - "Lewis H. Morgan as Field Worker", 1987
    - "Lewis H. Morgan as Historian", 1983
    - "Lewis H. Morgan: Man and Scholar", 1981 Nov. 13
    - "Lewis H. Morgan's Ethnographic Studiesof the Iroquois", 1981 Dec. 6
    - "Louis Henry Morgan: notes on possible illustrations", 1949-1993
      - Caroline G. Parker Mountpleasant, n.d.
  - M - Y (Box 11)
    - "A Method for the Study of CulturalThemes", 1952
    - "On Parsons and Shils", 1952?
    - "Papagos in Tuscson: An Introduction to Their History, Community Life, and Acculturation"--Master's thesis at University of Arizona, 1952; 2 Folders
    - "Preliminary Paper on the History of Some Southwestern Groups as Given in Their Migration Legends", 1954 Dec.
    - "Preliminary Report on the Social Survey of Pascua"--Paper for Anth. 222, 1950 Jan. 16
    - "Redfield's Definition of the Folk-Urban Continuum"--Paper for Socials Relations 209, 1953 Dec. 8
    - "Religion and Social Organization in theSouthwestern United States", 195-
    - "Ritual, Power and the Supernatural: A Comparative Study of Indian Religions in Southwestern United States"--Doctoral thesis at Radcliffe College, 1958 Mar.; 2 Folders
    - "The Scholar and Reform: The Case of Lewis H. Morgan", 1983
    - "Seneca Calendric Ceremonials at theTonawanda Longhouse"
      -See Ser.V, Tonawanda, Folder #2
    - "Social Organization of the Huron Indians", 1966
    - "Some Factors in the Navaho Death Complex"--Paper for Social Relations 161, 195-
    - "Some Reflections on Lewis H. Morgan's Study of Iroquois Sociopolitical Organization and Religion", 1981
    - "Some Reflections on Northern IroquoianCulture History and Its Study", 1968
    - "The Structure of Iroquois Religion", 196-
    - Unidentified, n.d.
      - Unidentified, 1967?
    - "The United States Constitution and theIroquois League"
    - "Women in Iroquois Society", 1975 Jul. 25
    - "The Yumans, Pimans and the Hohokam", 1954
      -See also Ser.I, Haury, Emil W.
    - "Ritual, Power and the Supernatural: Tooker, doctoral thesis--related photographs", 1954
      - Tohono O'Odham dwelling
    - "Morgan Collections book: Morgan book--plates (photos) for proposed book", n.d.
      - Carving false face mask, 1965
- Series IV. Works by Others, 1969-1989
  Works by Donald Bahr, Henry F. Dobyns, and Grace Rajnovich. There is a proposal and a report by Michael K. Foster for his 1970 research at the Six Nations Reserve, as well as an essay by Bruce G. Trigger for the Northeast volume of the Handbook of North American Indians.
  - B - T (Box 12)
    - "Oratory", 1988-1989; Bahr, Donald M.
    - "Some Personal Perspectives on Ethnohistory Practitioners", 1988 Apr. 24; Dobyns, Henry F.
    - "Reviving Indian Arts Among the Senecas", Fenton, William N., (William Nelson), 1908-2005; Hill, Cephas
    - "Formal Speaking on the Six Nations Reserve"--Research proposal, 1969?; Foster, Michael K.
    - "Interim Report on Field Work #1", 1970 Jul. 8; Foster, Michael K.
    - "Reviving Indian Arts Among the Senecas", Hill, Cephas
    - "Visions in the Quest for Medicine: An Interpretation of the Indian Pictographs of the Canadian Shield", 1989; Rajnovich, Grace
    - "Cultural Unity and Diversity in the Northeast", 1974; Trigger, Bruce G.
    - "Papago negatives, Louis Henry Morgan Library", n.d.
      - Tohono O'Odham couple, 1969-1989
- Series V. Field Notes, 1950-1982
  Tonawanda genealogies collected and revised by Tooker in July 1966 and then revised again by Veronica Evaneshko in January 1973. There are field notes about the Southwestern Yaqui Indians (in Pascua, Arizona), the Southwestern Papago Indians, and the Iroquois Tonawanda Reservation. There are also some notes taken at the American Anthropological Association meeting in 1982. This series contains one card file that is mainly about the Papago Indians; there are a few cards about the Yaqui Indians in the town of Pascua.
  - P- Tonawanda #6 (Box 13)
    - Papago
      - Folder 1, 1951
      - Folder 2, 1951
      - Folder 3, 1954
      - Folder 4, 1954
    - Pascua, 1950
    - Tonawanda
      - Folder 1, 1958-1959
      - Folder 2, 1959-1963
      - Folder 3, 1964 Jan.-Mar.
      - Folder 4, 1966 Aug. 1964-22 Jul.
      - Folder 5, 1966 Jul. 23-1972 Aug. 15
      - Folder 6, 1972 Aug. 16-17
  - Tonaw. Geneal. - Tonaw. Roch. (Box 14)
    - Tonawanda Genealogies, 1973 Jan.; 2 Folders
    - Tonawanda; Rochester; Oklahoma; AAA Meeting, 1972 Dec.-1982
  - Card File
    - Papago; Pascua (Yaqui Village), 1950-1951
- Series VI. Photographs, 1951-1973
  Photographs from Tooker's 1952 master's thesis, "Papagos in Tucson: An Introduction to Their History, Community Life, and Acculturation"; photographs (sent to Tooker by Janet S. Pollak) of chipped stone turtles; and a photograph (originally in the Papago card file in Series V) of a group of Papago Indians. There are also photographs of dioramas that are in the Museum of Arts and Sciences in Rochester, New York and in the Buffalo and Erie County Historical Society. These photographs were collected for possible use in the proposed tourist attraction, Iroquoia. (This note applies to images listed in the inventory)
  Native American Images note: Over 2,000 images, dated 1940-2000, scattered throughout all the Series, of many Native American tribes, primarily the Six Nations of the Iroquois and the Tohono O’odham (Papago). Nearly 300 black and white gelatin photographs of Tohono O’odham (Papago) in Tucson, Arizona taken by Tooker for her masters and doctoral theses from 1952-1958, of social customs including ceremonial dances, races, processions, and dwellings. Some are photographic reprints of Native American life ca. 1900 and 1925. Other images reflect Tooker’s professional research of proposed and published works such as the Louis Henry Morgan collection, anthropology in Philadelphia, Iroquois dioramas, and studies of wampum. Of note, is a cabinet card of Ely S. Parker’s sister, Caroline Parker Mountpleasant, a Seneca Indian of the Wolf Clan. Images from other sources include color photographs of the Neville Museum exhibit of the Iroquois and the Constitution, photomechanical prints of pictographs of the migration of the Akwesasne, and color slides of North American Indian tomahawks from the British Museum. Of local interest, a black and white photomechanical print from the Indiana University Museum of “Indians and cowboys assembled before Wanamaker’s” department store in Philadelphia, PA, 1908. The Oversize collection contains maps of Native American reservations in New York State, the area between Albemarle Sound and Lake Erie, and the southern and eastern boundaries of Pennsylvania.
  - I - T (Box 15)
    - Iroquoia--Dioramas, 1965
      - Iroquois diorama, 1965
    - Papago Group, 1951
    - "Papagos in Tucson: An Introduction to Their History, Community Life, and Acculturation", 1952
      - Tohono O'Odham woman, 1900
      - Tohono O'Odham settlement, 1952
    - Turtles. Chipped Stone, 1973